Why does the ball for the World Cup look
like this and not this? Turns out that
difference really changes how the ball
performs. And there's a third design
that's even more controversial. So, the
trick is figuring out the best way to
make a sphere out of a flat material.
Woke up balls usually start with one of
these basic 3D shapes with flat sides.
So, this year's ball started here. And
then they made each of the sides of the
triangle a little curvy, then a little
curvier. Then they folded up the four
panels into a ball. Tada. But what you
probably think of as a soccer ball
starts here. Chop off the points and
expand them to make 32 panels. But this
controversial ball combined both
techniques. They started here, chopped
off the corners, rounded the edges to
create what might be the roundest,
smoothest ball ever. But weirdly, it was
too round and too smooth. The airflow
would create a wake at the back,
producing more drag and making the ball
move uncontrollably. This same problem
is why golf balls have little grooves in
them to make their path more
predictable. So that's why this year's
ball has these extra grooves in it as
well. But there's also a secret sensor
inside this ball.